A Finding Aid to the Kimberly Camp Papers, circa 1970-2012, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Kimberly Camp papers
circa 1970-2012
Archives of American Art
Camp, Kimberly
AAA.campkimb
Archival Resource Key
9 Linear feet
The papers of painter, dollmaker, and arts administrator Kimberly Camp measure 9.0 linear feet and date from circa 1970 to 2012. The papers comprise biographical materials, including recordings of interviews with Camp; 12 journals/sketchbooks containing notes on professional activities and sketches; professional files documenting many aspects of Camp's career; printed materials featuring exhibitions of Camp's artwork and other material related to Camp's work as an artist and arts administrator; photographic materials including digital recordings of exhibitions; and unidentified audiovisual materials.
Biographical / Historical
Kimberly Camp (1956- ) is an African American painter, dollmaker, and arts administrator in Collingswood, New Jersey. She was the founding director of The Experimental Gallery at the Smithsonian Institution from 1989 to 1994, president of the Charles Wright Museum of African American History from 1994 to 1998, and executive director of the Barnes Foundation from 1999 to 2005. She was a fellow for the National Endowment for the Arts Expansion Arts Program in 1986 and a fellow at the Kellogg National Leadership Program from 1997 to 2000.
Camp received a B.A. from the University of Pittsburgh in studio arts and art history, and an M.S. in arts administration, and also participated in programs at Harvard Business School, University of Victoria, and Gallup Leadership Institute. She is the recipient of multiple awards including the Roger L. Stevens Award for Contributions to the Arts and Culture, National Conference of Artists National Service Award, and Purchase Award.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1981-2012 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 1, 10)
Series 2: Journals and Sketchbooks, 1975-2009 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, 8-10)
Series 3: Professional Files, 1983-2012 (4.0 linear feet; Boxes 2-4, 10-11)
Series 4: Printed Materials, 1980s-1990s (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 4-5)
Series 5: Photographic Materials, circa 1970s-2007 (1.0 linear feet; Box 6)
Series 6: Unidentified Audiovisual Materials, circa 1990s (0.4 linear feet; Box 7)
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter, dollmaker, and arts administrator Kimberly Camp measure 9.0 linear feet and date from circa 1970 to 2012. The papers comprise biographical materials, including recordings of interviews with Camp; 12 journals/sketchbooks; professional files documenting many aspects of Camp's career; printed materials featuring exhibitions of Camp's artwork and other material related to Camp's work as an artist and arts administrator; photographic materials including digital recordings of exhibitions; and unidentified audiovisual materials.
Biographical materials include appointment books, biographies, and recordings of interviews with Camp. Camps's journals/sketchbooks include notes on professional activities and sketches. Professional files consist of files for the Kellogg National Leadership Program, the Museum of African American History, and the Smithsonian Experimental Gallery, and include video and sound recordings of conferences and panels, project plans, and manuscripts and drafts of "Defending the Dead" by Camp. Printed materials document exhibitions of Camp's artwork and include the Auerbach Employee Handbook and Art Planète video magazine which featured artwork by Camp, in addition to other material related to Camp's work as an artist and arts administrator. Photographic materials include slides, born-digital recordings of exhibitions and Drexel University's centennial, photos of works of art, and personal snapshots. Also found are unidentified audiovisual materials consisting of video and sound recordings.
Conditions Governing Access
Manuscript drafts for "Defending the Dead: The Totally True Story of the Barnes Transformation"; an appointment book; a Museum of African American History journal; and Salzburg Seminar journal are access restricted; written permission is required. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings and born digital records in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Kimberly Camp papers were donated in 2016 and 2023 by Kimberly Camp.
Interviews; Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Arts administrators -- New Jersey; Dollmakers -- New Jersey; Painters -- New Jersey; African American artists; Women artists; Women painters; Women arts administrators; Barnes Foundation; Charles H. Wright Museum of African American History
- Biographical Materials, 1981-2012; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1, 10
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains 4 appointments books, a few biographies written about Camp, and recordings of interviews with Camp for Breakfast with the Arts, the Barnes Foundation, and Gateways Project in Ghana. The scrapbooks contain printed exhibition materials, clippings, correspondence, and award certificates, and other material related to Camp's career as an artist and as an administrator.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The appointment book from 1983 is access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  Arrangement
  The scrapbook pages were removed from 4 binders, but the original order of the material was maintained.
  - Appointment Book, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
    This appointment book is access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  - Appointment Book, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Book, 1993-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Book, 2002-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographies, circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interview Recordings, 1984-2001; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS); 1 Videocassettes (Video 8); 3 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    Interviews with Camp on video include Breakfast with the Arts Interview with Kimberly Camp from 2001, an interview for the Barnes Foundation, and interviews for Gateways Project in Ghana.
  - Personal Sound Recordings, 1984-1986; Archival Resource Key; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 7)
    The cassettes are labeled as party mix tapes, music by King Sunny Ade, and "Kimkins theme song" by Donovan Mixon, a National Endowment for the Arts fellow.
  - Scrapbooks, 1981-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-14)
- Journals and Sketchbooks, 1975-2009; Series 2; Archival Resource Key
  The series consists of 12 journals/sketchbooks dating from 1975 to 2009. Most of the books contain a mixture of meeting notes, thoughts about projects and art, and sketches and doodles. Included are notes on an NEA fellowship, the Reach Project, Detroit, the Museum of African American History, and Salzburg Seminar. The books marked as "decoy," "bogus," and "mock" contain the same mixture of notes and sketches as the other books in the series.
  The Museum of African American History book dated 1998 and the Salzburg Seminar book dated 1999 are access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  - Journal / Sketchbook, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes notes on the 1986 National Endowment of the Arts fellowship.
  - Journal / Sketchbook, Summer or Spring Drawings, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    2 small notepads
  - Journal / Sketchbook, Detroit, 1995-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, Detroit, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, Museum of African American History, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
    The Journal / Sketchbook, Museum of African American History, dated 1998 is access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  - Journal / Sketchbook, Salzburg Seminar, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
    The Journal / Sketchbook, Salzburg Seminar dated 1999 is access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  - Journal / Sketchbook, "Decoy Journal", 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, "Bogus Journal", 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, "Mock Journal", 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, Reach Project, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Journal / Sketchbook, Reach Project, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Professional Files, 1983-2012; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 4 Linear feet Boxes 2-4, 10-11
  Files in this series document Camp's professional activities while at the Smithsonian Institution's Experimental Gallery from 1989 to 1994 and at the Charles Wright Museum of African American History where she served as president from 1994 to 1998. Also documented is Camp's participation in the Kellogg National Leadership Program, various conferences and panels captured on sound and video recordings, and other events related to Camp's professional life. One file of correspondence is mainly professional and created during Camp's time at the Museum of African American History. A few personal letters are included from Narcissa Weatherbee and "Ed and Carol." Also in the series are manuscripts and drafts of "Defending the Dead" by Camp.
  "Defending the Dead" Manuscripts and Drafts in boxes 10-11 are access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  - American Association of Museums, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Brown Babies Company, Business Plan, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Camden City Cultural Commission, Case Study and Plan, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Conferences and Panels, Recordings, 1980s-1993; Archival Resource Key; 4 Sound cassettes; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes the People Puzzle Teleconference, Encouraging the Arts panel, Harrisburg panel, and an unidentified panel.
  - Correspondence, 1993-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Defending the Dead" Manuscripts and Drafts, 2010-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4-15)
    "Defending the Dead" Manuscripts and Drafts is access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  - "Defending the Dead" Manuscripts and Drafts, 2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1-17)
  - Gateways, Project Proposal, circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kellogg National Leadership Program, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Kellogg National Leadership Program, 1997; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Recordings are of Camp's "Vision Presentation" from 1997 and "A Legacy of Leadership."
  - Miscellaneous Recordings, 1985-1996; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS); 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Titles of recordings are King Monument SF, Kimkins Camden Historical Society, and American Urban Radio Networks.
  - Museum of African American History, General, 1990-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Museum of African American History, Annual Meetings, 1990; 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Museum of African American History, Publicity, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Museum of African American History, Publicity Report, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
  - Museum of African American History, Programs for Review, 1997; Archival Resource Key; 4 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    Recordings are review copies of AV1, Tableau7, and the Matrix.
  - Museum of African American History, Recordings, 1995-1997; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS); 2 Videocassettes (Video 8) (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Recordings of Applebaum exhibition design meetings and "raw footage" for the museum.
  - Museum of African American History, Recordings, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Recordings are of news stories featuring the museum.
  - Museum of African American History, Recordings, 1997-1998; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Recordings are of a city council meeting and the museum opening in 1997.
  - Nordic Museum Fair in Sweden, 1995-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Research Material on Education and Learning Styles, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Smithsonian Institution Experimental Gallery, Etiquette of the Undercaste, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Smithsonian Institution Experimental Gallery, Recordings, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Recordings are of George Awad *Powers of 10), a gallery tour, and news stories from The Today Show and WETA.
  - Smithsonian Institution Experimental Gallery, Recordings, 1992-1996; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Recordings are of Forward Motion from 1992, Kids Bridge and children's feelings about racism, and AWAD Astronomical Models (Power of 10).
  - Smithsonian Institution Experimental Gallery, Recordings, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key; 5 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Recordings include "Artists and Social Issues" panel discussion, Cositas concert and dance, Etiquette of the Undercaste, and "parents and children."
  - Smithsonian Institution Experimental Gallery, General, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Trip to Zihuatanejo, Mexico, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes material on African descendants in Mexico.
  - Texas Association of Museums, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Printed Materials, 1980s-1990s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  The series consists of announcements and catalogs for a few of Camp's exhibitions and exhibitions of other artists, the Auerbach Employee Handbook and Art Planète video magazine featuring Camp's artwork, and documentary and news recordings regarding cultural diversity, the contributions of African Americans, the Barnes Foundation, and other topics related to Camp's work and research, and miscellaneous newsletters and other paper and born-digital printed material.
  - Booklets, 1989-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - Documentary Recordings, "Cultural Diversity of the Arts: A National Report", 1988; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Documentary Recordings, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Recordings are by the American Psychological Association and William Greaves Productions.
  - Documentary Recordings, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Recordings are of "Barnes spots" on WHYY and The Africans Programs 106-109.
  - Documentary Recordings, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Recordings are of the Yellow Springs Institute Radio Documentary Series and "Contributions: African-Americans and the American Mosaic."
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Guide, "Girl Scouts, Science and Mathematics" Leader Manual, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Guide, Recruiting Non-Profit Board Members, 1995; Archival Resource Key; 1 Floppy disc (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Handbook Designed by Camp, Auerbach Employee Handbook, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Magazines and Newsletters, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Poems by John Paul Batiste, 1995-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Recordings of News Stories, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Recordings are of CBS morning show and of Nelson Mandela's release from jail.
  - Video Magazine, Art Planète Magazine, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1970s-2007; Series 5; Archival Resource Key
  Series includes snapshots of the Hurston Festival, video recordings of Camp's exhibitions and of Drexel University's centennial, and a digital slideshow from Camp Studios. Also found in the series is a large quantity of slides of works of art and mixed slides of events, travel, personal photos, and some works of art.
  - Camp in Drexel University Centennial, circa 1993; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Camp's Exhibitions, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Recordings are titled "Community Mirror" and "Caribbean Cultural Show" from 1988.
  - Camp Studios, Slide Show, 2007; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Snapshots of the Preserve Eatonville Community, Hurston Festival, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mixed Slides, circa 1970s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5-9)
  - Works of Art, Dolls, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Works of Art, Slides, circa 1970-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11-16)
- Unidentified Audiovisual Materials, circa 1990s; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 7
  The series consists of 8 video recordings and 1 sound recording that are unlabeled or have labels that do not provide enough information to determine content.
  - Unidentified Audiovisual Materials, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS); 1 Sound cassette (Box 7, Folder 1)
    The sound cassette is labeled "Rincon Criollo."
  - Unidentified Audiovisual Materials, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key; 8 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 2-4)